Preliminary Inventory to the Jay Calvin Huston papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jay Calvin Huston papers
1917-1931
47005
Hoover Institution Archives
14 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes, 1 microfilm reel (5.8 linear feet)
Writings, pamphlets, leaflets, and clippings relating to cultural, political, and economic conditions in China, and to communism and Soviet influence in China.
Huston, Jay Calvin.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
American consular official in China, 1917-1932.
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, pamphlets, leaflets, and clippings relating to cultural, political, and economic conditions in China, and to communism and Soviet influence in China.
United States. Department of State.; Communism--China.; China--Economic conditions--1912-1949.; China--Foreign relations--United States.; China--Politics and government--1912-1949.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--China.; China--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Diplomats--United States.
- Packages
  - I: Personal documents of M. Hassis, Soviet Vice-Consul in Canton (Box 1)
  - II: Communism - China (Boxes 1-3)
  - III: Civilization - China (Box 3)
  - IV: Student movement - China
  - V: Religion - China (Boxes 3-4)
  - VI: Political parties - China (Kuomintang) (Boxes 4-5)
  - VII: Labor and laboring classes - China (Boxes 5-6)
    - 1. General - History
    - 2. Strikes and lockouts
    - 3. Trade unions
  - VIII: Economic conditions - China (Box 7)
  - IX: Commerce - Customs - China (Box 8)
  - X: Foreign relations - China
  - XI: The United States and China (Box 9)
  - XII: The United States and Russia
  - XIII: Japan - Korea
  - XIV: Great Britain
  - XV: Russia (Boxes 9-10)
  - XVI: Miscellaneous (Box 11)
- Voluntary report, "What Will Be the Political Outcome of the KMT-Labor Communist Movement in China--Chaos and Sovietism, or a New Political Form in International Affairs?," draft (Box 12)
- Manuscript (typed, written), "The Rise of Modern Industrialism in China"
- Report, "The Labor Situation in China,", 1923 March 1
- Reports (carbons) re wreck and robbery of Tientsin-Pukov Express, with newspaper clippings, 1923 May 6
- Sun Yat-sen
  - Official proclamations (in English)
  - "The International Development of China," printed Program I: Part V (10 pp. plus 2 pp. diagrams)
  - "The International Development of China," printed Program II (pp. 11-30), diagrams inserted
  - Newspaper clippings from The Independent Herald, Hankow, entitled "Dr. Sun Yat Sen: The Father of Chaos" (7 pp.), 1925 February 3
- Extraterritoriality
  - Printed materials
    - Newspaper clippings
    - Pamphlets
  - Correspondence (one letter)
  - Summaries
  - Miscellany
- Printed materials
  - Chinese Correspondence (Vol. 2, Nos. 6-7)
  - Pan-Pacific Trade Union Conference
    - Bulletin of Proceedings, Hankow, 1927 May
    - Vol. 1, Nos. 1-5, 11-14, 1927
- Photograph (unidentified)
- "Civilization and Culture" - Newspaper clippings regarding various subjects (Tong Wars, etc.), circa 1922-1925 (Box 13)
- "Currency and Public Debts" - Copies of correspondence with Frederick Dumont, Commercial Office, State Department, 1928 December 31, 1929 January 22 and March 20
- "Chinese History" - Printed materials re Canton Incident, Japan, Soviet Union, etc.
- "Constitutional Government in China" - Printed materials
- American policy in China
  - Printed materials
  - Miscellaneous
    - Memo on American Policy in China - Past, Present and Future
    - Rockhill's memorandum on the Open Door Policy in China
    - Letter (carbon) to Secretary of State (No. 2636) from Jay C. Huston (2 pp.)
    - Report (corrected), "Encouragement of the Importation of Specified Classes of Commodities into U.S. and Extension... (of U.S.) Investments... (in) China,", 1921 October 20
- Report (carbon), "The Chinese Renaissance and Its Relation to Soviet Policy in the Far East," Sec. 1., 1923 August 8; Ibid, Sec. II, 1922 September 15
- Miscellaneous materials
  - "Political," (9 pp.) by C. P. Murray, 1929 April 1
  - Revised regulations of the Mutual Assistance Society (or Chinese Socialist Society of Canton) (22 pp.)
  - Editorials, Peking and Tientsin Times, 1922 May 6-27
  - "A Review of Political Conditions in the Canton Consular District," (51 pp. plus enclosures), 1927 December 31
  - Ibid (23 pp. plus enclosures), 1927 December
- Report, "The Significance to Foreigners in China of the Anti-Christian Outburst" (37 pp. plus enclosures), 1924-1925
- Report, including introduction with description of contents, pp. a-j. Subject: political situation in China, 1911-1924 (and Hankow, 1925 January-March), undated
- Sun Yat-sen - Miscellaneous typed and written materials; report regarding the Foreign News Services of China by Don D. Patterson, 1922 January 15
- Printed material (Box 14)
  - American Foreign Service Journal, 1932 August
  - Reply Letters by S. P. Smith to R. F. Johnston's Letters to a Missionary, Commercial Press, Ltd., Shanghai, 1919
  - Printed address by Byron Brenan, H.B.M.'s Consul-General at Shanghai, entitled The Office of District Magistrate in China, Shanghai, 1899
- American Trust publication, Review of the Pacific (various issues), 1927-1929
- Miscellaneous reports, manuscripts
  - Prominent Men in the KMT (translation of Soviet reports), 1926 May
  - Spread of Labor Union Movement... Yangtsze Valley (4 pp.)
  - Sketch history of Chinese Communist Party (40 pp.)
  - Voluntary report, "Will Chinese Capitalism Be Willing to Save China from Chaos and Communism?" (49 pp.), 1931 November 15
  - "Peasant, Workers, Soldiers Revolt of at Canton" (53 pp. plus enclosures). Addressed to J. V. A. MacMurray, American Minister, Peking, 1927 December 11-13
  - Political conditions in Canton District (13 pp. plus enclosures). Addressed to F. L. Mayer, 1927 October
  - Political conditions in Canton Consular District (12 pp. plus enclosures). Addressed to F. L. Mayer, 1928 March
  - Comments on a book (typed)
  - Political report (carbon), undated
  - "Communism in South China: The Hai-Lu-Fend Soviet" (carbon manuscript) (15 pp.), 1928 February 7
- Jay Calvin Huston, "Sun Yat-sen, the Kuomingtang and the Chinese Russian Political and Economic Alliance," typescript draft (187 p.)
- Jay Calvin Huston, "Sun Yat-sen, the Kuomingtang and the Chinese Russian Political and Economic Alliance," typescript draft (216 p.) (Reel 1)